<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<chapter>
<title>Graphical User Interface (libm4dWidgets)</title>

<para>
</para>

<section>
<title>Toolkits</title>
  <section>
  <title>Qt</title>

  <para>
  The MedV4D project uses the Qt library to create and manipulate GUI elements. Qt is a very powerful, object oriented,
  cross platform GUI library. Since it has an X Window System implementation as well as a Windows implementation,
  it allows the software to run under Windows and Unices as well. It works together very well with many other useful toolkits,
  one of which is the VTK (Visualization Toolkit) toolkit, which is also used as an optional component of the software.
  </para>
  <para>
  Qt uses QObject as a base of all its objects, and a special macro - Q_OBJECT - to inform Qt's preprocessor that the object
  contains Qt signals and slots. Signals are special functions without body that can be connected with slots, which causes
  the connected slot(s) to be called when the signal is emitted.
  </para>
  <para>
  Further, Qt uses QWidget as a base of all its GUI component objects. There are container widgets, which can be used to
  contain more widgets. This allows the programmer to create more complicated GUI interfaces.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>VTK</title>

  <para>
  VTK is a very complicated and large toolkit for visualizing a large number of data types. Its robustness and size is the
  reason that the project uses it only as an optional component for visualizing volume data in a 3D scene.
  </para>
  <para>
  A special Qt widget, called QVTKWidget, is used to incorporate VTK into the Qt GUI interface.
  </para>

  </section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Architecture</title>

<para>
Public and private declarations are in namespaces <code>M4D::GUI</code>, <code>M4D::Viewer</code> and <code>M4D::Selection</code>.
</para>

  <section>
  <title>M4D::GUI</title>

  <para>
  In this namespace, there are classes representing GUI components (except viewers). Most of the widgets can be used independently,
  not just how they are used in the base application. Extensibilty is also a big advantege of the design of GUI. New widgets
  can be added easily, especially viewers - for this reason, this framework is perfect for testing new types of viewers too.
  </para>

    <section>
    <title>Creating a new application</title>

      <para>
      Author of the new application has almost nothing to do. For a simple application is enougth to derive a class from
      <classname>m4dGUIMainWindow</classname> and you get every widget you should need, ready to use.
      </para>

      <para>
      The main program should be as following (where <classname>mainWindow</classname> is the derived class):
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[
#include <QApplication>

#include "mainWindow.h"

#include "Common.h"
#include <fstream>


int main ( int argc, char *argv[] )
{
  std::ofstream logFile( "Log.txt" );
  SET_LOUT( logFile );

  D_COMMAND( std::ofstream debugFile( "Debug.txt" ); );
  SET_DOUT( debugFile );

  QApplication app( argc, argv );
  app.setQuitOnLastWindowClosed( true );

  mainWindow mainWindow;
  if ( mainWindow.wasBuildSuccessful() )
  {
    mainWindow.show();
    return app.exec();
  }
  else
  {
    QMessageBox::critical( &mainWindow, QObject::tr( "Exception" ), mainWindow.getBuildMessage() + QString( "\n\n" ) +
                           QObject::tr( "The application will now terminate..." ) );
    return 1;
  }
}
]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    For sure, you will need to add some special funcionality to the GUI of the application - some widgets controlling the
    pipeline/filters (with resources such icons); reimplemented functionality at processing the resuls of search; connections, where can be connected
    viewers in the pipeline.
    </para>

    <para>
    The following code segment shows widget and pipeline connection adding
    (taken from the <classname>mainWindow</classname> constructor - the derived class)
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
createMyPipeline();

// tell mainWindow about possible connections - can be during the creation of pipeline (connections)

addSource( conn, "Bone segmentation", "Stage #1" );
addSource( conn, "Bone segmentation", "Result" );

// add your own settings widgets

addDockWindow( "Bone Segmentation", myPipelineWidget );
]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    To change the functionality at processing the resuls of search just reimplement the <classname>m4dGUIMainWindow</classname>'s
    process method (in the derived class <classname>mainWindow</classname>). The default behavior is: it creates
    image from the Dicom Object Set and sets it as input of the currently selected viewer. It looks like:
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
AbstractImage::AImagePtr inputImage = ImageFactory::CreateImageFromDICOM( dicomObjSet );

try {
  AbstractImageConnection *conn = new AbstractImageConnection();
  conn->PutImage( inputImage );

  mainViewerDesktop->getSelectedViewerWidget()->InputPort()[0].UnPlug();
  conn->ConnectConsumer( mainViewerDesktop->getSelectedViewerWidget()->InputPort()[0] );
}
catch ( ... ) {
   QMessageBox::critical( this, tr( "Exception" ), tr( "Some exception" ) );
}
]]>
    </programlisting>


    </section>

  </section>

  <section>
  <title>M4D::Viewer</title>

  <para>
  In this namespace, there are classes that visualize the data passed by the image processing pipeline. These classes have many signals
  and slots to connect to the other GUI components in M4D::GUI namespace.
  </para>

    <section>
    <title>m4dGUIAbstractViewerWidget</title>

    <para>
    This class is the base of all the viewer widget classes. It is an interface to declare the necessary methods, slots and signals
    to manage the viewer subclasses, which makes it possible to add a viewer widget to another GUI component through this interface,
    no matter what type of viewer it is.
    </para>
    <para>
    There is an operator () for downcasting every viewer widget to the appropriate QWidget so that it could be added to a GUI component.
    There is also a function that tells which slots are implemented in the given type of viewer ( different viewers have different
    functionalities ). Other GUI components use this to know which slots should be connected.
    Mouse buttons can be set and different modes can be set to personalize the viewer's behavior.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section>
    <title>m4dGUISliceViewerWidget</title>

    <para>
    This class is used for visualizing the image data slice by slice. Each slice is a 2D image, which can be set to be selected and
    drawn according to the xy, yz or zx axis. Images are diplayed using OpenGL textures. Image data comes through the image pipeline,
    which needs the libImaging library to be linked.
    </para>

    <para>
    There are two helper classes to handle generics in Imaging library (since Qt does not allow using templates).
    </para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem><para>
      VoxelArrayCopier simply arranges the voxels in the source array so that it could be displayed according to the slice orientation
      with the help of using strides (see Imaging library).
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
      TexturePreparer prepares the texture to be mapped and displayed. It also fills up images that are not powers of 2, so that older
      graphics cards can map and display the texture as well.
      </para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
    The viewer can display one slice or more slices at a time, it can display text information and handle mouse event according to mouse
    event handling settings, which can be set by a special method called setButtonHandler.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section>
    <title>m4dGUIVtkViewerWidget</title>

    <para>
    This class basically uses VTK to visualize the dataset in 3D. Datasets are converted to volume object, and mapped into a vtk scene.
    This is done by the libVTKIntegration library and VTK itself. For further information see the VTK manual or the libVTKIntegration
    section.
    </para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>M4D::Selection</title>

  <para>
  This namespace contains two classes, one for selecting points, and another one for selecting shapes. Shapes are nothing more than a collection
  of points.
  </para>

    <section>
    <title>m4dPoint</title>

    <para>
    This is a template class for points. It can set/get point values and dimensions, and it can measure point distances and also midpoints
    between two points.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section>
    <title>m4dShape</title>

    <para>
    This is a template class for shapes. It contains a list of its points ( a list of m4dPoints ). Besides adding and erasing points, this
    class can also calculate the centroid and the area size of a shape provided that the whole shape lies on the plane of the slice. For
    correct calculation and display, the slice's orientation has to be set.
    </para>

    </section>
  </section>

</section>

</chapter>
